{"test_questions": [[{"question": "120, 99, 80, 63, 48, ?", "opta": "35", "optb": "38", "optc": "39", "optd": "40", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The pattern is - 21, - 19, - 17, - 15,.....So, missing term = 48 - 13 = 35."}, {"question": "589654237, 89654237, 8965423, 965423, ?", "opta": "58965", "optb": "65423", "optc": "89654", "optd": "96542", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The digits are removed one by one from the beginning and the end in order alternatelyso as to obtain the subsequent terms of the series."}, {"question": "3, 10, 101,?", "opta": "10101", "optb": "10201", "optc": "10202", "optd": "11012", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Each term in the series is obtained by adding 1 to the square of the preceding term.So, missing term = (101)2 + 1 = 10202."}, {"question": "In the series 2, 6, 18, 54, ...... what will be the 8th term ?", "opta": "4370", "optb": "4374", "optc": "7443", "optd": "7434", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, 2 x 3 = 6, 6 x 3 = 18, 18 x 3 = 54,.....So, the series is a G.P. in which a = 2, r = 3.Therefore 8th term = ar8-1 = ar7 = 2 x 37 = (2 x 2187) = 4374."}, {"question": "125,80,45,20,?", "opta": "5", "optb": "8", "optc": "10", "optd": "12", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The pattern is - 45, - 35, - 25, .....So, missing term = 20 - 15 = 5."}, {"question": "1, 1, 4, 8, 9, 27, 16, ?", "opta": "32", "optb": "64", "optc": "81", "optd": "256", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The series consists of squares and cubes of consecutive natural numbers i.e. 12, 13, 22, 23, 32, 33, 42, .....So, missing term = 43 = 64."}, {"question": "1, 2, 3, 6, 9, 18, ?, 54", "opta": "18", "optb": "27", "optc": "36", "optd": "81", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The pattern is x 2, x 3/2, x 2, x 3/2, x 2,.....So, missing term = 18 x 3/2 = 27."}, {"question": "6, 13, 25, 51, 101, ?", "opta": "201", "optb": "202", "optc": "203", "optd": "205", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The pattern is x 2 + 1, x 2 - 1, x 2 + 1, x 2 - 1,.....So, missing term = 101 x 2 + 1 = 203."}, {"question": "5,6,9, 15, ?, 40", "opta": "21", "optb": "25", "optc": "27", "optd": "33", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The pattern is + 1, + 3, + 6,....., i.e. + 1, + (1, + 2), + (1 + 2 + 3),.....So, missing term = 15 + (1 + 2 + 3 + 4) = 25."}, {"question": "1, 3, 4, 8, 15, 27, ?", "opta": "37", "optb": "44", "optc": "50", "optd": "55", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The sum of any three consecutive terms of the series gives the next term.So, missing number = 8 + 15 + 27 = 50."}, {"question": "3, 4, 7, 7, 13, 13, 21, 22, 31, 34, ?", "opta": "42", "optb": "43", "optc": "51", "optd": "52", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The given sequence is a combination of two series :I. 3, 7, 13, 21, 31, ? and II. 4, 7, 13, 22, 34The pattern in I is + 4, + 6, + 8, + 10,.....The pattern in II is + 3, + 6, + 9, + 12,.....So, missing term = 31 + 12 = 43."}, {"question": "198, 194, 185, 169, ?", "opta": "92", "optb": "112", "optc": "136", "optd": "144", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The pattern is - 4, - 9, - 16,.....i.e. - 22, - 32, - 42,.....So, missing pattern = 169 - 52 = 169 - 25 = 144."}, {"question": "2, 3, 5,7,11,?, 17", "opta": "12", "optb": "13", "optc": "14", "optd": "15", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, the given series consists of prime numbers starting from 2. So, the missingterm is the prime number after 11, which is 13."}, {"question": "6, 12, 21, ?, 48", "opta": "33", "optb": "38", "optc": "40", "optd": "45", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The pattern is + 6, + 9, + 12, + 15, .....So, missing term = 21 + 12 = 33."}, {"question": "Which term of the series 5, 10, 20, 40, ..... is 1280?", "opta": "10th", "optb": "9th", "optc": "8th", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, 5 x 2 = 10, 10 x 2 = 20, 20 x 2 = 40,.....So, the series is a G.P. in which a = 5 and r = 2.Let 1280 be the rath term of the series.Then, 5x2n-1 = 1280  2n-1 = 256 = 28  n - 1 = 8  n = 9."}, {"question": "2, 5, 9, ?, 20, 27", "opta": "14", "optb": "16", "optc": "18", "optd": "24", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The pattern is + 3, + 4, + 5, + 6,.....So, missing term = 9 + 5 = 14."}, {"question": "2, 3, 3, 5, 10, 13, ?, 43, 172, 177", "opta": "23", "optb": "38", "optc": "39", "optd": "40", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The pattern is + 1, x 1, + 2, x 2, + 3, x 3, + 4, x 4, + 5.So, missing term = 13 x 3 = 39."}, {"question": "9, 27, 31, 155, 161, 1127, ?", "opta": "316", "optb": "1135", "optc": "1288", "optd": "2254", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The pattern is x 3, + 4, x 5, + 6, x 7,.....So, missing term = 1127 + 8 = 1135."}, {"question": "2, 1, 2, 4, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 8, 10, 11, ?", "opta": "9", "optb": "10", "optc": "11", "optd": "12", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The given sequence is a combination of three series :I. 1st, 4th, 7th, 10th, 13th terms i.e. 2, 4, 6, 8, ?II. 2nd, 5th, 8th, 11th terms i.e. 1, 4, 7, 10III. 3rd, 6th, 9th, 12th terms i.e. 2, 5, 8, 11Clearly, I consists of consecutive even numbers. So, the missing term is 10."}, {"question": "Which of the following will not be a number of the series 1, 8, 27, 64, 125,.....?", "opta": "256", "optb": "512", "optc": "729", "optd": "1000", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The given series consists of cubes of natural numbers only. 256 is not the cube ofany natural number."}, {"question": "13, 32, 24, 43, 35, ?, 46, 65, 57, 76", "opta": "45", "optb": "52", "optc": "54", "optd": "55", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The given sequence is a combination of two series:I. 13, 24, 35, 46, 57 and II. 32, 43, ?, 65, 76The pattern in both I and II is + 11. So, missing term = 43 + 11 = 54."}, {"question": "22, 24, 28, ?, 52, 84", "opta": "36", "optb": "38", "optc": "42", "optd": "46", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The pattern is + 2, + 4, + 8, + 16,.....So, missing term = 28 + 8 = 36."}, {"question": "3, 15, ?, 63, 99, 143", "opta": "27", "optb": "35", "optc": "45", "optd": "56", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The terms of the given series are (22 - 1), (42 - 1),....., (82 - 1), (102 - 1), (122 - 1).So, missing term = (62 - 1) - (36 - 1) = 35."}, {"question": "90, 180, 12, 50, 100, 200, ?, 3, 50, 4, 25, 2, 6, 30, 3", "opta": "150", "optb": "175", "optc": "225", "optd": "250", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, 90 = 30 x 3, 180 = 6 x 30, 12 = 2 x 6, 50 = 25 x 2, 100 = 4 x 25, 200 = 50 x 4.So, missing term = 3 x 50 = 150."}, {"question": "48, 24, 96, 48, 192, ?", "opta": "76", "optb": "90", "optc": "96", "optd": "98", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The pattern is \u00f7 2, x 4, \u00f7 2, x 4, .....So, missing term = 192 \u00f7 2 = 96."}, {"question": "2,15,41,80,?", "opta": "111", "optb": "120", "optc": "121", "optd": "132", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The pattern is + 13, + 26, + 39,.....So, missing term = 80 + 52 = 132."}, {"question": "6, 11, 21, 36, 56, ?", "opta": "42", "optb": "51", "optc": "81", "optd": "91", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The pattern is + 5, + 10, + 15, + 20, ...So, missing term = 56 + 25 = 81."}, {"question": "563, 647, 479, 815, ?", "opta": "672", "optb": "386", "optc": "279", "optd": "143", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The pattern is + 84, - 168, + 336,.....i.e. + 84, - (84 x 2), + (84 x 22), .....So, missing term = 815 - (84 x 23) = 815 - 672 = 143."}, {"question": "13, 35, 57, 79, 911, ?", "opta": "1110", "optb": "1112", "optc": "1113", "optd": "1315", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The terms of the given series are numbers formed by joining together consecutiveodd numbers in order i.e. 1 and 3, 3 and 5, 5 and 7, 7 and 9, 9 and 11, .....So, missing term = number formed by joining 11 and 13 = 1113."}, {"question": "1, 4, 10, 22, 46, ?", "opta": "64", "optb": "86", "optc": "94", "optd": "122", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The pattern is + 3, + 6, + 12, + 24,.....So, missing term = 46 + 48 = 94."}, {"question": "66, 36, 18, ?", "opta": "3", "optb": "6", "optc": "8", "optd": "9", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Each term in the series is the product of the digits of the preceding term.So, missing term = 1 x 8 = 8."}, {"question": "In the series 3, 9, 15, ...... what will be the 21st term?", "opta": "117", "optb": "121", "optc": "123", "optd": "129", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Clearly, 3 + 6 = 9, 9 + 6 = 15,.....So, the series is an A.P. in which a = 3 and d = 6.Therefore 21st term = a + (21 - 1) d = a + 20d = 3 + 20 x 6 = 123."}, {"question": "28, 33, 31, 36, ?, 39", "opta": "32", "optb": "34", "optc": "38", "optd": "40", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The pattern is + 5, - 2, + 5, - 2,.....So, missing term = 36 - 2 = 34."}, {"question": "1, 9, 25, 49, 81, ?", "opta": "100", "optb": "112", "optc": "121", "optd": "144", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The series consists of squares of consecutive odd numbersi.e. 12, 32, 52, 72, 92,.....So, missing term = 112 = 121."}, {"question": "1, 9, 25, 49, ?, 121", "opta": "64", "optb": "81", "optc": "91", "optd": "100", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The given series consists of squares of consecutive odd numbersi.e. 12, 32, 52, 72,.....So, missing term = 92 = 81."}, {"question": "2,2,5, 13,28,?", "opta": "49", "optb": "50", "optc": "51", "optd": "52", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The pattern is + 0, + 3, + 8, + 15, ..... i.e. + (l2 - 1), + (22 - 1), + (32 - 1), + (42 - 1), .....So, missing term = 28 + (52 - 1) = 28 + 24 = 52."}, {"question": "0, 2, 8, 14, ?, 34", "opta": "20", "optb": "23", "optc": "24.", "optd": "25", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The pattern is + 2, + 6, + 6, + 10, + 10,.....So, missing term = 14 + 10 = 24."}, {"question": "1, 5, 14, 30, 55, 91, ?", "opta": "130", "optb": "140", "optc": "150", "optd": "160", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The pattern is + 4, + 9, + 16, + 25, + 36, ..... i.e. + 22, + 32, + 42, + 52, + 62,.....So, missing term = 91 + 72 = 91 + 49 = 140."}, {"question": "In the series 10, 17, 24, 31, 38,.....which of the following will be a number of the series ?", "opta": "48", "optb": "346", "optc": "574", "optd": "1003", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The given series consists of numbers each of which, on dividing by 7, leaves aremainder 3. No other number except 346 satisfies the property."}, {"question": "240, ?, 120, 40, 10, 2", "opta": "180", "optb": "240", "optc": "420", "optd": "480", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The pattern is \u00f7 1, \u00f7 2, \u00f7 3, \u00f7 4, \u00f7 5.So, missing term = 240 \u00f7 1 = 240."}, {"question": "2,3,8,27, 112,?", "opta": "226", "optb": "339", "optc": "452", "optd": "565", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The pattern is x 1 + 1, x 2 + 2, x 3 + 3, x 4 + 4,.....So, missing term = 112 x 5 + 5 = 565."}, {"question": "6, 17, 39, 72, ?", "opta": "83", "optb": "94", "optc": "116", "optd": "127", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The pattern is + 11, + 22, + 33, .....So, missing term = 72 + 44 = 116."}, {"question": "20, 20, 19, 16, 17, 13, 14, 11, ?, ?", "opta": "10, 10", "optb": "10, 11", "optc": "13, 14", "optd": "13, 16", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Let the missing terms of the series be x1 and x2.Thus, the sequence 20, 20, 19, 16, 17, 13, 14, 11, xv x2 is a combination of two series :I. 20, 19, 17, 14, x1 and II. 20, 16, 13, 11, x2The pattern in I is - 1, - 2, - 3,......So, missing term, x1 = 14 - 4 = 10.The pattern in II is - 4, - 3, - 2,......So, missing term, x2 = 11 - 1 = 10."}, {"question": "24, 60, 120, 210, ?", "opta": "300", "optb": "336", "optc": "420", "optd": "525", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The pattern is + 36, + 60, + 90,.....i.e. + [6 x (6 + 0)], + [6 x (6 + 4)], + [6 x (6 + 9)],...So, missing term = 210 + [6 x (6 + 15)] = 210 + 126 = 336."}, {"question": "625, 5, 125, 25, 25, ?, 5", "opta": "5", "optb": "25", "optc": "125", "optd": "625", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The given sequence is a combination of two series :I. 625, 125, 25, 5 and II. 5, 25, ?The pattern in I is \u00f7 5, while that in II is x 5. So, missing term = 25 x 5 = 125."}, {"question": "10, 100, 200, 310, ?", "opta": "400", "optb": "410", "optc": "420", "optd": "430", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The pattern is + 90 + 100, + 110,.....So, missing term = 310 + 120 = 430."}, {"question": "11, 10, ?, 100, 1001, 1000, 10001", "opta": "101", "optb": "110", "optc": "111", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The pattern is - 1, x 10 + 1, - 1, x 10 + 1, - 1, x 10 + 1, .....So, missing term = 10 x 10 + 1 = 101."}, {"question": "2, 7, 27, 107, 427, ?", "opta": "1262", "optb": "1707", "optc": "4027", "optd": "4207", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The pattern is + 5, + 20, + 80, + 320, ...... i.e. + (5 x 12), + (5 x 22), + (5 x 42), + (5 x 82),.....So, missing term = 427 + (5 x 162) = 427 + 1280 = 1707."}]]}